In this series we’ve talked quite
a bit about goods and services.
Now it’s time to look at the people who
produce all those goods and services.
These are people who perform labor, which means
they must have a job. But how do we determine
who has a “job” and who doesn’t? The answer is
actually more complicated than one might think.
Economists define the labor force as all
nonmilitary people who are both employed
and unemployed. However, different countries
often define the labor force in different ways.
In the United States, the Bureau of Labor
Statistics determines how many people are
in the labor force. They consider people to be
employed if they are 16 years or older and meet at
least one of the following requirements. One, they
worked at least one hour for pay in the past week.
Two, they worked fifteen or more hours
without pay in a family business.
Or three, they held jobs but did not work due
to either sickness, vacation, labor disputes,
or bad weather. Typically, those who are
not included in the labor force include
full-time students, stay-at-home parents, retired
people, active military, the institutionalized,
and those who have given up looking for
employment for an extended period of time.
What if someone has more than one job? They’re
still only counted once in the labor force.
Technology is constantly changing the labor
force. In the early days of the United States,
most citizens were farmers. Throughout the
1800s, however, the economy transformed
due to the Industrial Revolution, a time
of rapid economic expansion caused by the
shift from agriculture and production by hand
to factories and production using machines.
By the early 1900s, heavy manufacturing had
become the main driver of the American economy.
In the second half of the 1900s, a boom in
electronics created a new wave of factory
jobs. Beginning in the 1970s, the revolution
in personal computers led to yet another boom.
Due to rapidly changing technology, over the past
few decades service-producing industries have
been far outpacing good-producing industries.
Globalization has also dramatically changed
the labor force in recent years. While the
number of service jobs has increased, the
United States has lost millions of manufacturing
jobs, mostly due to outsourcing and offshoring.
Outsourcing is when a company contracts with
another company to do a specific job that would
otherwise be done by a company’s own workers. Most
companies outsource work in at least some way.
Offshoring is when a company shifts some of
its operations, or resources of production,
to another country. More often than not, companies
outsource and offshore in order to save money,
as they can pay workers in other countries
less than workers in their own country.
As less-skilled manufacturing jobs moved
overseas, the Americans who had filled
these jobs had to find new work, and many had
to go back to school or enter new job training
programs in order to gain new skills. Because
of this, it is increasingly the case that a high
school diploma alone is not enough to prepare
Americans for financial success. Therefore,
post-secondary education has skyrocketed
in popularity over the past few decades.
Economists have two explanations for the
connection between educational advancement
and higher wages. The first theory, called the
learning effect, says that education increases
efficiency of production, and therefore leads
to higher wages. The second theory, called the
screening effect, says that the completion
of college signals to employers that a job
applicant is both intelligent and hard-working.
Other trends in recent years include a shift
toward a more diverse labor force, an increase
in part time workers, and a shift toward what
is known as a “gig economy.” A gig economy is
a labor market characterized by freelance work,
as opposed to permanent jobs. Instead of a worker
staying with one company, in a gig economy that
worker would have short-term contracts with
various companies. Whatever career you decide on,
you will have to be prepared for change, as labor
markets are increasingly dynamic. At some point in
your life, you will almost certainly be a part of
the labor force, whether you want to be or not. So
it’s best to be prepared in advance, which means
we’d better continue to learn about economics.